A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Africa and Middle East Programs (AME), Program Staff Files FA503
Rockefeller Archive Center
In the 1980s, Carmichael and others, with strong support from Thomas and the board, continued the 1970s' support of South African grantees for training large numbers of black lawyers and litigating sensitive cases in the South African legal system. Recognizing the multifaceted nature of discrimination in South Africa, the Foundation not only advanced the rule of law, but also strengthened civic organizations, women's groups, and educational institutions. Further, it supported a number of activist organizations in the United States that were energetically advocating US governmental sanctions against South Africa and for private disinvestment. The Foundation also played a role in shaping US policy on apartheid through the role Thomas played from 1985 to 1987 chairing the US Secretary of State's Advisory Committee on South Africa.
The Foundation's overseas staff also sought to improve the economic situation in poor, marginalized communities through targeted loan programs particularly to women head of households, beginning with the innovative work in Bangladesh of Professor Mohammed Yunus, the founder of the Grameen Bank. The results led the way to establish the field of microfinance with the aim of empowering women living in poverty conditions, such as through a microfinance network in Latin America starting 1980 and a global lending program for women starting in 1987.
Thomas encouraged staff to share results at worldwide meetings. During those meetings, Ford staff in the country offices and in New York tried to follow the mandate to work as "one foundation." The persistent challenge toward meeting that goal, however, was that initiatives emerging from the New York-based programs, or indeed any program developed in one country, were not always adaptable, relevant or acceptable in other countries or regions. It remained a challenge to develop a unified program, despite the commitment at the highest level of foundation leadership.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Summary - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
During this era, the Foundation's earlier interest in business and the economy evolved into a commitment to improving conditions for people living on the margins of society. The Ford Foundation promoted advancements in women's rights around the globe and introduced micro-lending into grantmaking. At the same time, the economic issues that were shaping program strategies also affected the Foundation's assets. Severe cuts resulted in a significant restructuring of country programs and reduced budgets across all programs.
Even with the cuts in country offices, in the 1970s Ford grantees in developing countries received approximately 80% of the International Division budget. The remaining fifth went to Population, Development Studies, and International Affairs. Although representing a much smaller piece, the International Security and Arms Control program from 1973 was the Foundation's most concerted effort to make meaningful inroads in disarmament and nuclear issues - those challenges most directly linked to the Foundation's historic concern for peace. By 1979, the Ford Foundation was the biggest funder of arms control as a field, both in the U.S. and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Sketch - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Between 1989 and 1991, dramatic changes in the external international conditions created a significantly different context for Ford Foundation's international activities both in the United States and overseas. In November, 1989, the Berlin Wall fell. In February 1990, in South Africa, Nelson Mandela was released from prison. In December 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved. As a consequence, the Cold War was over, Western Europe no longer had a special strategic role in the Foundation, and program-related activities in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union multiplied. The Foundation not only continued the earlier efforts to fund leadership in the region; from 1990-1994, Ford also spent $1 million on the training of newly-elected parliamentarians in Eastern Europe and the former USSR. By 1993, half of the funds for grantmaking related to the former Soviet bloc were going to in-country individuals and institutions.
In 1989, Thomas also instituted a major restructuring of the Foundation to fulfill his vision of "One Foundation." All programs were put into one division led by Vice President Susan Berresford. Carmichael joined the Institute of International Education to run a program on Soviet and Eastern European Affairs and then higher education in South Africa. All the Foundation grant programs - domestic and international - reported to Berresford: Africa and the Middle East (AME, formerly MEA), Asia (ASIA), Latin American and the Caribbean (LAC/OLAC), Human Rights and Governance (HRG), Education and Culture (EC), Program-Related Investments (PRI), and International Affairs (IA).
The change in South Africa opened up many new opportunities to work in partnership with a range of South Africa partners to promote and sustain the transition to democracy. The Foundation supported women's groups working on law, development and reproductive rights. It contributed, for example, to the groups working on the Women's Chatter in South Africa, resulting in the adoption in 1994 of the first constitution anywhere that specifically included sections on women's rights.
During the 1990s, the promising political changes in African countries and elsewhere provided a positive perspective to counteract the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and the rising debt in developing countries. Both to reinforce local democratic initiatives and to address its economic challenges, the Foundation's field offices across Africa and the developing world shifted their support toward the promotion of smaller scale community-based initiatives.
Thomas supported work on arts and culture, not as a goal in itself, but, instead, as a means for promoting social justice, education, and human rights, both in the United States and in developing countries. At the same time, while reducing support for cultural institutions in the United States, such institutions received support overseas to preserve and celebrate national and local cultural heritages. While in South Africa, for example, the Foundation provided support for Johannesburg anti-apartheid theatre groups, in West Africa it funded for nearly two decades a program to preserve and make accessible cultural heritage by expand the training of museum leaders and strengthening museum exhibit and outreach capabilities.
In the early 1990s, the Foundation through its India office helped establish an independent foundation to enhance sustainability in the arts community. Ford envisioned new opportunities for cultural institution to rely on local resources focus on new forms of creativity and encourage young artists, in particular. Similar to the Indian effort, the Ford office in Egypt in 1993 provided support for an arts-focused foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, with a strong commitment to globalization as well as concern for the uncertainty it created, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action, an organizational goal that had been initiated in the Bundy era.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women's issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. The more promising international situation enabled the Ford Foundation in 1996 to open an office in Russia (Moscow) and in Vietnam (Hanoi). Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries. A regional security, peace, and cooperation program in India, for instance, focused on the work of civil society groups as an increasingly prominent regional interest in South Asia.
In this period, the Foundation gave renewed the prominence of arts and culture in the US and maintained the commitment in developing countries. By 2000, funding levels for the Education, Media, Arts and Culture division were approaching parity with the other two, Assets and Peace and Justice.
Berresford also encouraged each of the programs to hold worldwide meeting to promote cross-program and cross-national collaboration in fields such as human rights, income generation, cultural preservation, and building capacity in the arts and arts management. One persistent question of such initiatives. Toward that end, and building on the earlier experiences in India and Egypt, Berresford worked closely with her senior vice president, Barry Gaberman and other staff to establish new foundations at the local and national levels, particularly in developing countries. Gaberman had been at the foundation since 1973, starting as assistant to the representative in Indonesia. After serving in a number of different positions, by 1984, under Thomas, he served as deputy vice president in the U.S. and International Affairs program. After the 1989, Thomas and Berresford appointed him deputy vice president. 1996, Berresford appointed him senior vice president.
As the twentieth century came to a close, the economic conditions of the 1970s and 1980s that had resulted in so much global debt, with special impact on the developing world, were slowly turning around. Many countries were experiencing economic growth and burgeoning democratic initiatives. Not only was the global economic situation improving but the Foundation's assets were also growing. Consequently, the Foundation was in a strong position to bring attention to long-standing issues holding back developing countries. The grants programs addressed the pressing need both for advanced training of young- to mid-career adults living in marginalized and disadvantaged conditions along the equally, and for strengthening and building sustainability of universities across sub-Saharan Africa, along with enhancing broadband access for improved internet communications, promoting women in higher education, and strengthening postgraduate education.
Reacting to the tragedy of September 11, 2001, the Foundation provided immediate relief to affected local institutions in the United States. The Foundation also helped launch support a fund at the Institute of International Education to support scholars at risk in countries in conflict and under terrorist threats, especially in, but not limited to, the Middle East.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Summary - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Franklin Thomas's presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation's US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women's rights. Throughout Thomas's tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation's time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford's encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Meeting and Discussion Group Records, 1966-1976, 1987-1992; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of correspondence, agenda, rapporteur notes and memoranda from Foundation staff who attended meetings and discussion groups. The records document internal Foundation meetings and working groups such as division conferences, as well as external meetings, conferences and working groups where Foundation staff met with representatives of other foundations or foreign governments. There also are files for the Donors in African Education working group and a file on the Ford Foundation's relations with the government of Sudan.
  - Law and Development Conference -- reports (separated) and outline of possible topics, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society of International Law -- Panel on U.S. Law Schools and Developing Countries by Robert H. Edwards, Feb 15, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (1 of 3), May 1968-Jan 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (2 of 3), May 1968-Jan 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Legal Center -- Research and Training Committee (3 of 3), May 1968-Jan 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee on Women -- memoranda, reports, notes re: the position of women at the FF, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - International Division Conference, Sep 1975 (1 of 2), Sep 9, 1975-Dec 1, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Division Conference, Sep 1975 (2 of 2), Apr 4-Sep 4, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Women -- memoranda and discussion papers on women's programming at the FF, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - West Coast Trip -- Notes and Schedule, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Council on Foundations -- notes, correspondence and background for a meeting of the committee on international grantmaking, Dec 18, 1987-May 12, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - World Conference on Philanthropy, Mar 1, 1988-Feb 20, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1989 Dakar Human Rights Meeting -- Rapporteur Notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Program Review 1989 -- Rapporteur Notes, Jan 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Donors in African Education, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Interview Skills Seminar, Oct 26, 1989-Jan 22, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sudan Government Relations, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reproductive Health Meeting, Jun 28, 1990-Dec 6, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sterling Forest/Tuxedo Governance Meeting, Jul 6, 1990-Oct 29, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - African Development Finance Conference, Aug 18, 1990-Oct 18, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Africa LEIG Meeting, Dec 26, 1990-Oct 18, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Donors in African Education, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - African Museums Meeting, Mar 1, 1991-Aug 21, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - MacArthur Foundation Meeting, Mar 4, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Council on Foundations, Chicago, IL, Mar 14, 1991-Apr 24, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Africa/Middle East Regional Program Review, Jul 8, 1991-Jan 16, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reproductive Health Meeting, Aug 7, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rural Poverty and Resources Meeting, Aug 24, 1991-Feb 3, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - African Rural Poverty Meeting, Aug 18, 1991-Jan 20, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bellagio Conference, Aug 26, 1991-Sep 19, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Nelson Mandela Luncheon, Oct 30, 1991-Dec 4, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Harvard Center for International Affairs -- Political Liberalization in Africa, Nov 20, 1991-Mar 8, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - DAE Working Group on HE, Nov 25, 1991-Feb 8, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Africa Staff Meeting, Dec 10-12, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Worldwide International Affairs Program Meeting, Dec 28, 1991-Oct 26, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - South Africa, Jan 13, 1992-Feb 22, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - International Conference on Culture and Development, Feb 17, 1992-May 12, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Namibia/South Africa, Apr 21, 1992-Aug 6, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - John Gerhart Meeting Correspondence 1992, May 19-Nov 18, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - South Africa Visit, Sep 21-22, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - South Africa Trip, Oct 15-Dec 14, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Memoranda, Bulk, 1985-1994 1965-1968, 1985-1994; 1985-1994; II
  This series combines the files of three past program officers. Anna Wadia's memo files for 1992-1994 focus on grant proposals or grant-related meetings. Her files also contain correspondence between program staff. Robert Edward's files hold Foundation memoranda on the U.S. Balance of Payments (1965-1968), and Steven Riskin's files describe the political situation and repercussions for ordinary Sudanese during the civil war in Sudan (1985-1992) and South African television and newspaper ownership (1992-1994).
  - U.S. Balance of Payments, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sudan, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reflections on Foundation Programming Related to Disaster Preparedness and Response, Feb 10, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Higher Education in Africa, Apr 16, 1989-Jul 10, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 7th United Nations North American Regional NGO Symposium on the Question of Palestine, Jun 27-29, 1990, Jul 9, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - South Africa Media, Sep 29, 1992-Jun 5, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File -- Meetings, Grant Updates (1 of 4), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (2 of 4), Jan-Jul 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (3 of 4), Aug-Dec 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Anna Wadia Memoranda File (4 of 4), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Reports, Bulk, 1989-1990 1965-1990 (bulk 1989-1990); 1989-1990; III
  This series includes a 1965 report on "Planning the Receipt of Aid" and a 1990 program strategy paper on "Planning for Democratic Governance and Public Policy in Eastern and Southern Africa."
  - "Planning the Receipt of Aid" by O. S. Knowles, Aug 1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Programming for Democratic Governance and Public Policy in Eastern and Southern Africa: A Program Strategy Paper", Jan 2, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Trustee-Related Records, 1991-1992; IV
  This series documents visits by several Foundation trustees to Namibia, Nigeria, Senegal and Zimbabwe. The files hold correspondence, notes, travel agenda, briefing material, and biographical information about the trustees.
  - Frances Fergusson Visit to Southern Africa, Sep 25, 1988-May 15, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Senegal, Aug 20-Oct 25, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Preiskel/Ridings Africa Visit, Sep 18-Nov 24, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Nigeria, Sep 25-Oct 16, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Zimbabwe, Sep 27-Oct 16, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Namibia Visit, Jan 9-Feb 14, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)